we're going to continue our discussion
on weather derivatives and specifically
temperature options here we're going to
do statistical analysis on temperature
data here in sydney over the last 150
years we're going to look at this
bimodal temperature distribution and
look at the differences between weather
and winter periods and maximum and
minimums over given months we're then
going to use time series classical
decomposition to be able to de-trend and
then remove seasonality from our data
set once we do that we're going to use
an auto-regressive model a time series
model to be able to model the errors
that we're left with so just a quick
summary of our goal of the series which
is actually to price temperature options
now a quick reminder that the underline
here is heating degree days and cooling
degree days index over a given period so
these hdd and cdd indexes are based off
the approximation of average temperature
which in many places around the world is
just the average between the observed
maximum and minimum temperatures
throughout the day
so for an individual day we have an hdd
of the t of the maximum of zero between
the t reference temperature or base
temperature minus this average
temperature and for cooling degree days
it's just the opposite so the hdd and
the cdd index for a given period in for
example the winter period or the summer
period is just going to be the summation
of all those days hdds their heating
degree days or the cooling degree days
over that given period now the option
payoff is really only limited by the
fact that it's based on this heating
degree day or cooling degree day index
but other than that let your imagination
run wild but exemplar products that
actually trade otc are for example the
call with a cap and this is the form
where you take the minimum of a
either the cap
commonly 500 or 1 million dollars usd
and this average rate payoff for every
heating degree day over a specified
strike now obviously it's opposite for
the put so with that goal in mind let's
move on to the data set that we're going
to be using here in australia i live in
sydney and i'm really interested in
actually doing a bit of a weather
analysis of the sydney data set now the
data set that i'm using is from bomb the
bureau of meteorology here in australia
and here we can actually get data going
back to
1859 which is pretty incredible i've had
to stitch two bits of data together
looks like they've got a recent weather
station and update at the observatory
hill the link is here and in the
description
so with those two weather stations in
mind i've stitched that data together
downloaded it from the website and then
got the csv files now the data available
essentially i've got maximum
temperatures and minimum temperatures
now for
those of you who don't live in australia
sydney is on the east coast of australia
in new south wales and if we zoom in
it's right near the sydney harbour
bridge
observatory hill is there so we're going
to be looking at these two weather
stations
at that location over the last year
greater than 150 years
so let's import our dependencies we've
got numpy pandas datetime and matplotlib
here i'm just going to reference where
i've downloaded those maximum
temperature and minimum temperature
files and essentially here's what one of
them look like i've got product code a
bomb station number so that that weather
station number i've got years months
days maximum temperature this is the
column that i'm interested in and then
the quality of the data now because this
data set is so large and goes back so
many years it's good to check for
missing data so if i have missing data
for one the max temperature or the
minimum temperature then i'm not going
to be able to compute my average
temperature within that specific day so
we'd have to remove that row completely
so
i'm checking for nulls here and here
we've got true
153 from the max and 153 for the min but
like i just said these might not be
occurring on the same day which is
annoying
so i asked myself the question are these
occurring on the same day and what we
can do we can just zip
these two
data frames where this is null
and i want to return back if these are
occurring at the same point and we in
fact find out that 41 of the 153 missing
data points do not occur on the same day
so that's annoying i'm just going to
have to remove all those rows after i
make the
transformation of that average
temperature so here i've got a bit of
code that i've
created and cleaned up the max and min
temperature data frame remember i'm only
interested in the maximum temperature
column and the minimum temperature
column and then the actual date
so i change everything to date times i
apply that change to the data frames set
the indexes date
drop all the other columns and then what
i'm going to do is rename the maximum
temperature column and minimum
temperature columns to tmax and t-min
then i can join the two data frames and
i join them as an inner on left and
right on both the date indexes
once i've done that i can use a function
average temp and that's just going to
take the row t max and t min and divide
it by two and then once i've done that
now i'm going to drop all rows
on n a values and remember i have to do
that because if i didn't have one
particular temperature for a min and max
i am not going to have a correct
average temperature
so once we've done that our data frame
looks like this and i've got dates tmax
tmin and temperature to look at some
general statistics about this we can
look at
the describe function from pandas this
gives us a count on all the rows of data
so you know nearly 60 000 rows
daily information of temperature which
is crazy we can look at the means of the
t-max t-min and then average temperature
standard deviation
and then some of the percentiles and the
min and max
now this min and max is pretty cool but
this is over the entire period what
happens if we want to
look down at particular months or
seasons to get a better better idea of
what the max and means have actually
been so first thing i'm going to do i'm
going to indicate the winter and summer
period so here in australia i've got
winter being the period from may to
october and then summer from november to
april so i'm going to do a deep copy on
my temperatures data frame and then i'm
going to label
a season as the month which i'm just
taking the index month i'm then making a
mask which is uh the specific
temperature
um season of the months for winter and
then i'm applying that mask to my filter
making the indicator equal to one if
it's winter and then i just do the
reverse for summer now visualizing the
data here's just a time series plot of
our three indicators t max t min and
temperature over the uh plus 150 years i
mean so it's not very useful i can't
really see any oscillations so let's
zoom in a little bit i'll just look at
the last
5 000 um or you know 12 year period
and here what we've got is we can see in
blue our t-max t-min is below and we can
see these huge cycles
and variation in the data
so let's take a better look at the
temperature distributions so for this
i'm going to be looking at histogram
plots
so here our histogram plot of the t-max
is in blue
t-min is in
this orange color and then we've got a
bimodal distribution here for our
average temperature
and what we can actually see is this
biomodal distribution with two means the
means are actually centered and reflect
the peaks of both the summer and winter
months and to show that we can then
use our indicators for our summer and
winter months separate this distribution
into two histograms and show that over
time here is my
slightly negatively skewed distribution
um for the winter months and then
somewhat more normally looking
distribution for the summer months so
interesting here to see that the
temperature distribution
in the southern hemisphere here is
negatively skewed so now i'm quite
interested in seeing the temperature
records that have actually materialized
for particular months and this is just
satisfying a curiosity but you could do
it on whatever season you want so let's
first compile a list of min and max
records for each month on record so the
way i'm doing this i'm compiling a date
list
for my time series data frame i then
need to re-sample on the monthly starts
and then i'm going to aggregate the min
and max now once i've done that i can
aggregate a data frame
for each particular starting month with
the min of that month and then the max
of that month
i can then
create a index which is going to be the
month that's on so 1 3 to 12 from
january to december and we can aggregate
that on that later
then we can subsection our original data
frame temps
each time based on what month we're in
and here we're just going to take the
maximum temperature and we're going to
take the max of the maximum temperature
observed and the min of the maximum
temperature observed and then the max
and min of the temperature min observed
we're also going to do this for our
average temperature so i know that's a
bit confusing but we yeah essentially
we're looking at the max and min that is
observed within a particular month of
the t-max the t-min and the temperature
profile so let's take a better look at
the temperatures extremes that exist on
record now that we can group these
seasons however we like so we're going
to look at the maximum maxes and the
minimum t mins because obviously this is
the most interesting we're also
interested in looking at the maximum t
mins that were observed and the minimum
t maxes so here this is like the maximum
temperature that you might observe for a
particular month you might be interested
in seeing the maximum t min in the
winter months
once we apply that group by we end up
with a data frame like this and
interesting to see that the highest
temperature on record that i can see for
the sydney observatory is
45.8 and obviously you can go back
through the data and look up where that
occurred now the minimum temperature
that i can observe that's happened on
record at the sydney observatory is
actually in the june period here at 2.1
but it's important to know that
the
min
temperature the maximum of the min
temperatures that have ever been
observed during that height of the
winter period
for june is actually 18.4 so it's
interesting to see these swings in the
extreme temperatures
over that well 170 year period nearly
now we're going to look at our
underlying which is that average
temperature indicator so we're going to
look at the maximum and minimum
observed for
each individual month we're also going
to look at the maximum t mins and the
minimum t maxes so this is our actual
underlying data that average t um t and
we're interested in the maximum and
minimums observed so that's how you can
compile it for different seasons now
that we've looked at the statistics
let's jump into how to decompose this
using time series so now we're actually
going to model and do time series
decomposition so this is a technique
that splits the time series into several
components each representing an
underlying pattern in the data so here
we're going to talk about trend
seasonality and noise now usually
there's a third component called cycles
but this is actually going to be taken
up in classical decomposition into the
trend component so really it's a trend
and cycle component so is the trend
decreasing constant or increasing over
time what is the periodic signal for the
seasonality and the noise so the
variability in the data that cannot be
explained by the model this is really
the remainder
so by stats models seasonal decom
composition this is a naive
decomposition used in python and it uses
classical decomposition so what is
classical decomposition well essentially
the additive model is of this form here
again we have our time series varying
with t with our trend component our
seasonal component and then our error
term so the algorithm is using a
convolution filter on the data the trend
is removed and then the average of this
detrended series is
used
for each period to actually return the
seasonal component the steps for
classical decomposition are as follows
so here
for the trend cycle component over a
given period m so the period we're going
to define
we can get a moving average term then we
can take this away from our original
time series to get the d trended series
the estimated seasonal components is
then calculated by averaging the d
trended values for that season and in
our case this is going to be every day
within the year so the seasonal
component values are then adjusted to
ensure they add to zero and then this
remainder and error term is just
calculated by subtracting the trend and
the seasonality from our original data
set so we'll talk about the
disadvantages of using classical
decomposition in a minute but for now
let's import our dependencies so from
stats models
let's import the ad fuller test which is
the unit
stationary test we'll import seasonal
decompose we'll use the plot acf and
plot pacf for
partial autocorrelation functions and
autocorrelation functions autoreg aer
select order and then auto reg results
again our temperature frame is going to
be i'm just going to sort on the index
which is our date and here's what it
looks like we've got tmax tmin and
temperature remember we're only
interested in temperature
and then our date time series goes from
january 1859 all the way through to
today
now let's just take a brief look at our
data set here we have a clear upward
trend in temperature over time i've just
taken a rolling window of 10 years i got
the mean and plotting that over time and
here you can see that up dripped over
time and i've also taken the variance
over that time window as well and you
can see that variance has definitely
changed over that time period
so with that in mind let's use our
seasonal decompose function so here
we're going to use that additive model
that we spoke about before
we're going to pass in our time series
temperature of just t that average
temperature indicator now because we
have such a long time series uh with
something like 15 to 16 decades um i'm
going to choose a moving average term uh
period here uh of 10 years now this this
is kind of crucial for getting a bit of
a smooth trend function um but obviously
if you want to discretize a little bit
more you can change that to 365. and
i'll just show you actually what that
looks like so if we use 365 you can see
that the trend series
gets a lot of variability within that
moving average over a one year period
whereas we're kind of smoothing that out
over a ten year period and then more of
the variation ends up in our residuals
in our seasonal components we've then
taken the decomposed result and then we
can break it down to a trend our
seasonal and our residual
now that's just the complete.plot that
we're visualizing there but let's
but because everything's so jammed up
and there's so many seasonal patterns to
actually visualize that properly let's
look over a 10-year period so here i'm
just looking at the trend at the top our
seasonality and then our residual
component so the first thing that you're
going to notice is the fact that there
is this
ugly straight line at the end of our
data set and the reason that's there is
because we've taken a 10-year moving
average now this is a two-sided moving
average which means it's taken five
years at the end of the time series and
five years at the start of the time
series so there's no real moving average
term that's actually calculated over
those periods
so what you can do is you can set it
equal to the frequency and yeah
essentially it's just extrapolation
and that's what we've done but that is
actually one of the downsides that's uh
actually noted in the documentation on
classical decomposition that i've given
you in the link there one of the other
biggest downsides is the fact that
you'll be able to see here our
seasonality component has captured a
good five degree swing that's occurring
every year
but you'll see here that there's kind of
some really strong what i would call
auto correlation in our residual
components and we'll see that soon but
this looks like you could almost
decompose that further into a seasonal
component now the issue here is that
classical decomposition function
looks over a specified amount of time
and with that particular function that
we're using there it's always a one year
period
now that's kind of annoying because
perhaps we have some peculiarities
within our temperature series that means
that we've actually got
some other period or an offset
to our yearly seasonal function which it
looks like here our peaks are kind of
occurring maybe you know 90 days or half
a year beforehand in our residuals so
unfortunately classical comp
decomposition isn't really picking this
up now despite its limitations we've got
another methodology that we're going to
be looking at later so we're going to
roll on with classical decomposition so
before we do any time series um
decomposition on our residuals now we
need to confirm that this residual time
series is actually in fact stationary
before we do any ar
or armor models let's perform the diki
fuller test and essentially this is just
a unit root test where the null
hypothesis is that a unit root exists
aka random walk so essentially here what
we're going to do is test the last 5 000
data points
and see
what the results are and whether it's
statistically significant or whether we
have enough information to determine um
whether a unit root exists or not
now we've got our
ad f statistic back and that's yielding
a p-value of .0015
and that means that we've got enough
statistical evidence to reject the null
hypothesis that the unit root exists
that doesn't mean that it doesn't exist
it just means that given how data set
these are the results we've got if you
include all the data set because we have
60 000
data points
using the adf
methodology it gets extremely likely
according to the test that
there is no
unit root existing here the residual
distribution here i've got a histogram
and essentially it looks really normally
distributed
however we know that there is serious uh
auto correlation so yeah the analysis of
serial correlation or auto correlation
is just the correlation that occurs uh
in the areas in the residuals from one
time point
on itself so what is the correlation
between a time point in the errors
now compared to the last moment in time
compared to the last day and so on
so we're observing massive auto
correlation positive auto correlation
all the way up until really 90 days and
then after that it just turns negative
so exactly what this plot's showing is
that we have huge seasonal
relationships in our
residual terms over time
now obviously there's significant serial
correlation here and since the auto
correlation function does not seem to
vanish after a number of lags
we are not going to try and fit a moving
average term instead we're going to try
and determine um the number of or the
order of the autoregressive model
and we're going to do this by looking at
the partial autocorrelation function and
then the aic
criterion so first off the partial order
correlation function
basically instead of finding
correlations or the present values of
lags
on all the data set from different days
it finds the correlation of the
residuals
so what do we mean by that the residuals
remain after removing the effect which
are already explained by earlier lags
so uh with respect to the next time lag
so here in the graph below we've already
found huge explanation through the first
two lags and that's not taken into
consideration in the third lag term
there whereas if you remove the effects
of those first two then you get our
partial auto correlation on the third
one in our partial acf function
so essentially we remove already found
variation before we find the next
correlation and here we can see that
there's a significant partial auto
correlation in our first two days and
then it kind of decreases all the way to
15 here even 20. now the archaic
information criterion so aic this is a
single number score and essentially this
is just representative of model fit and
here we have two components
so this term here is about fit and this
is using the log likelihood
and the likelihood is the maximum
likelihood estimator of the fit of a
particular model and k is just the
number of parameters that that model has
so this is about judging parsoname now
what we're trying to do here is get the
best fit without over complicating or
overfitting the model so as we increase
the number of parameters obviously the
model gets more complex but we want to
optimize and get the best fit so the way
that we're trying to optimize here we're
using the aic criteria to get the best
fit
that it kind of reduces the number of
parameters so we actually want the
lowest aic value we can but within
reason
so the best balance of model fit with
generalizability this is serving the
eventual goal of actually maximizing our
fit out of sample
so let's look at the residuals
we're going to test the residuals on
a lag term up to 40 with our ar model
and we're going to use the aic model
to actually sort on so here in our graph
we can see the aic
value that actually decreases as we
increase the number of lags that's
included in our autoregressive model and
as you can see as we get to 15 it goes
down to about 1.26 and there's not
really a huge decrease in the aic after
that it goes down to 1.25 in our 20 and
then even smaller decrease after we
increase um lag so i'm going to make the
decision here that we're going to fit an
ar model with 15 lags now we're going to
fit our autoregressive model with 15
lags and we're going to use the autoreg
functions for that on the residuals lags
equals 15 and then we're going to fit
the model we can then look at the params
the residuals and we're going to most
importantly look at the dot summary
evaluation so the most interesting row
to look at is going to be our z scores
and then the probability
of these z scores so essentially what
we're doing here is the null hypothesis
test the null hypothesis test being that
this is uh equal to that the coefficient
is equal to zero and what we want to do
is we if we if that's really powerful
and we have statistical evidence to
prove that that is not the case then um
we would reject the null hypothesis at a
diff at a a given critical level
so what we have here is that the
intercept has a probability of um 89. so
if we set our critical value to say five
percent um well then we cannot reject uh
the null hypothesis that this is
statistically insignificant so what
we're going to do is we're actually not
going to include the intercept so the
way we do that is we just include trend
n
for no
and essentially then we get our other
coefficients without the intercept now
you'll see all the other um
all the other p values here for our
estimates over these coefficients are
zero so we have to reject the null
hypothesis and say that they are
statistically significant and for such a
large um number of observations
and given the fact that
we need to capture this seasonality that
is definitely present within the
residuals um that makes a lot of sense
to me
we also get the percentiles of this
estimate um
which are shown here so our coefficient
estimates are here our parameters that
are estimates and then the percentiles
around those estimates are here so
taking a plot of what those residuals
look like
after we take into consideration that ar
15 model well essentially now our
residuals
look like this
but we can't really see much there so
let's zoom in on the last 200 data
points and you can see this looks a lot
more like a white noise process
essentially now we have auto correlation
um and partial auto correlation
functions that have almost zero auto
correlation between um different lags
and this is exactly representative of a
white noise process obviously there are
other tests that you can do to test
whether it's a white noise process we
might go through that in
another video okay so now that the
serial correlation appears to have been
captured within this ar model now we
have our trend component we've got our
seasonality component and then we've got
a model for our residuals which is an
auto regressive model with 15 lag terms
so in the next video instead of using
classical decomposition we're actually
going to use fourier series to represent
our seasonal component of our data set
so see you in the next one
[Music]
you